Guide to the William L. Crosten Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
William L. Crosten papers
1952-2001
SC0765
Crosten, William L. (William Loran), 1909-2001.
0.5 Linear feet
Collection includes biographical materials; several typescript articles; lecture notes; assorted programs, clippings, and press releases on Stanford performances; and notes, lists, and typescript histories of Stanford's music department and programs.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
William Loran Crosten established the Stanford Music Department and served as its chair from 1947 to 1973 when he retired. He earned his doctorate in musicology from Columbia University in 1946; as a scholar he specialized in opera history and aesthetics.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes biographical materials; several typescript articles; lecture notes; assorted programs, clippings, and press releases on Stanford performances; and notes, lists, and typescript histories of Stanford's music department and programs.
Access Terms
Crosten, William L. (William Loran), 1909-2001.; Stanford University. Department of Music.; Stanford University. Libraries. Music Library
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Biographical materials, including his obituary and memorial program, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1967-71 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "American Music Comes of Age" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Creative Music in the United States during the Period 1900-1935" (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Operas of Gian-Carlo Menotti" (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Story of 'The Count Ory'" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Word and Tone in Purcell's Dramatic Music: Some Rhythmic Aspects" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Musicians biographies (William Turner Walton, Arthur Seymour Sullivan, Manuel de Falla) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wagner: Tristan prelude – mss lecture with music notation (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lecture notes with music notation – Bach chorale #23 and Schubert waltz Op. 18 no. 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Opera notes (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1956-2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ballad of Baby Doe (includes Crosten's article, clippings, and program), 1956-61 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stanford performances, assorted programs, clippings, press releases, 1952-86 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Music Library – notes and history (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Stanford's Early Music Program, history of (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Music Education Program, history of (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - History of Stanford's Music Department, mss notes (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faculty appointments, lists (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence (mostly invitations to musicians to come to Stanford), 1953-69 (Box 1, Folder 20)